Guide to the Diane Sands Papers 1892-2000 (Bulk: 1964-2000)
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Diane Sands Papers
1892-2000 (Bulk: 1964-2000)
University of Montana--Missoula Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 505
Sands, Diane
10.0 linear feet
The collection primarily contains the papers of women’s organizations and women’s movements that Diane Sands, an activist in Montana, was associated with from the 1970s to the 1990s. The collection includes papers of the Women’s Resource Center, the Missoula Chapter of the National Organization for Women, the Montana Pro-Choice Coalition, and the Women’s Lobbyist Fund as well as papers related to the development and history of the Women’s Studies department at the University of Montana. The collection also contains materials related to the women’s liberation movement of the 1960s and 1970s. The papers of the Montana Women’s History Project papers are also included in the collection and contain transcripts of oral histories with Montana women as well as records of the Illegal Abortion in Montana Oral History Project including interviews, correspondence, research notes and publications.
Biographical Note
Haysel Diane Sands was born in 1947 in St. Ignatius, Montana and grew up on Indian reservations where her parents taught school. She attended high school in Frazer, Montana on the Fort Peck Indian Reservation. She received her B.A. in Anthropology from The University of Montana, Missoula in 1974 with an emphasis in American Indian culture and social organization. She attended George Washington University in Washington DC from 1974-76 completing courses toward a master’s degree in Women’s Studies with an emphasis on public policy and non-profit organizational development. During her time at The University of Montana, Sands was a member of several student activist organizations including Students for a Democratic Society, and a member of the early women’s liberation movement in Missoula. She participated in the creation of conscious-raising programs on campus, which met regularly at the Women’s Action Center (1969–1974), which eventually became the Women’s Resource Center (1974–1986) where Sands and others taught women’s studies courses without the approval of the university.
Diane Sands was the director of the Montana Women’s History Project from (1975-1990). She researched, designed and presented educational programs, courses, conferences, and publications focusing on women’s history and oral history. From 1984-1994, Diane Sands was the Executive Director of the Montana Women’s Lobbyist Fund, a non-profit, non-partisan coalition of 52 organizations organized to develop public policy, organize communities and lobby the Montana Legislature on a wide range of social and economic policies of benefit to women and families. Sands served as Campaign Manager for the “No on One” campaign in Boise, Idaho in 1994 and successfully defeated Proposition One, an anti-gay ballot measure. Diane Sands was elected to the Montana State House of Representatives in November 1996 representing the North and Westside, downtown, and the Rattlesnake of Missoula, Montana. As a legislator, she focused on affordable housing, healthcare, welfare reform, and issues to improve the lives of children. She has been the Co-Project Director of the Montana Feminist Project since 1999 and has worked tirelessly to collect and interpret the history of the second wave of feminism and women leaders from 1960-2000 in Montana and to create avenues for public education and discourse. From 2001-2003, she held the position of National/State Relations liaison for the Montana Office of Public Instruction. She was the Program Director of the Montana Community Foundation from 2003-2004 and in 2005 served as the Interim Director of the Partnership Health Center in Missoula, Montana. She has held numerous positions in local and state organizations including the founding President and Board Member of the Montana Oral History Association, a member of the Board of Directors of the National Women’s Studies Association, and the Regional Coordinator of the Northwest Women’s Studies Association. She was also the Program Director of the American Association of University Women and has been on the Montana Rhodes Scholarship Selection Committee since 1994.
She has won numerous awards including the Montana Committee for the Humanities Award in 1986, the Montana Business and Professional Women’s Montana Woman of the Year Award in 1993, Office of Public Instruction Equity Award for Public Service in 1991, the Missoula YWCA Silver Award for Public Policy 1986, The Missoula American Association for University Women named endowment in 1994, and the Montana AIDS Coalition “Heart and a Half Award” in 1989.
A majority of the materials in the collection document the activities of women’s organizations and oral history projects Diane Sands created or was affiliated with in Montana from the 1960s through the 1980s. The collection consists of reports, correspondence, oral history interviews, publications, photographs, conference papers, flyers, legislation, and memorabilia related to the history of the women’s movement in Montana in the 1960s through 1990s. Materials include the records of the Women’s Resource Center at the University of Montana (1970-1992), the records of the Missoula Chapter of the National Organization for Women (1982-1991) as well as the records of the Montana Pro-Choice Coalition (1971-1989) and the Women’s Lobbyist Fund (1982-1995). The collection also contains the records of the Montana Women’s History Project (1892-1996), which consists of oral histories and research notes of Montana women as well as oral history interviews and research notes of Montana women who participated in the Illegal Abortion in Montana Oral History Project (1913-1996). The collection also includes papers which document the development and history of the Women’s Studies program at The University of Montana (1964-1999) as well as the history of women’s liberation (1954-1982).
This collection has been divided into eight series:
Series I: Women’s Resource Center (1970-1992) is divided into two subseries, Administrative Records and Subject Files. Subseries 1, Administrative Records, documents the daily activities of the Center and primarily contains budget requests, forms, funding documents, minutes, meeting notes, correspondence, and daily logs of individuals who visited the Resource Center.
Subseries 2, Subject Files, is an alphabetical arrangement of materials that support or document the activities of the Women’s Center. Records include lobbying materials such as petitions, letters and notices about a battle to keep the space allotted to the Women’s Center in the University Center on the campus of The University of Montana.
The Women’s Resource Center was established as a volunteer organization to advocate for the rights of women, provide education, distribute information and raise awareness of women’s issues including abortion rights, birth control, women in the workforce, political activism, rape and violence against women, sexual harassment and discrimination, feminism, and equality. The Women’s Resource Center exists today as the Women’s Center and is located in the University Center on the campus of The University of Montana.
Series II: National Organization for Women, Missoula Chapter (1982-1991), is arranged chronologically and contains materials related to Montana from the national, state and local levels of the National Organization for Women. Items include minutes, newsletters, reports, conference materials, newspapers, posters and publications about gender issues and gay rights. Subseries 1, Subject Files, consists of administrative records, reports, conference materials and publications of the Missoula chapter of the National Organization for Women. Subseries 2, Non-Gender Insurance, contains records kept by Sharon Eisenberg as State Coordinator of Montana National Organization for Women. Items include reports, surveys, legislation, and correspondence related to non-discrimination insurance policies and laws.
Series III: Women’s Studies at the University of Montana (1964-1999), is an alphabetical arrangement of topics related to the development and implementation of the women’s studies program at the University of Montana. Items include reports, correspondence, and proposals regarding the need for a women’s studies program. Other items include research materials, syllabi, readings, student papers and exams, and evaluations of courses that were created and taught in the women’s studies department.
The Women’s Studies program at The University of Montana was officially created in 1991 but the history of its development begins in the 1960s when individuals began to petition the university to include academic courses about women’s issues, campaigned for equal rights in the workplace, created equal opportunity programs and wrote proposals for interdisciplinary programs in the 1970s which led to the approval but not the funding for a Women’s Studies program.
Series IV: Montana Pro-Choice Coalition (1971-1989), is arranged alphabetically by topic and contains materials related to the battle over the reproductive rights of women in the 1970s and 1980s. Subseries 1, Administrative Records, contains committee work, correspondence, legislation, and publications of the Montana Pro-Choice Coalition. Subseries 2, Abortion, includes information about abortion laws as well as publications, petitions and correspondence related to the campaign to repeal the Montana Abortion Control Act of 1974.
Series V: Women’s Liberation (1954-1982), is arranged alphabetically by subject and contains materials related to the women’s movement of the 1960s and 1970s. Many of the items are in reference to women’s liberation, a title applied to the second wave of feminism and the re-emergence of a public battle of women’s rights. Materials include reports, phone lists, handbooks, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, articles, and a box of posters as well as photographs of the One Woman Walkout in Helena, Montana (1977).
Series VI: Women’s Lobbyist Fund (1982-1995), consists of two subseries, Administrative Records, and Subject Files. Subseries 1, Administrative Records, primarily contains financial statements, minutes, correspondence, testimony and publications related to the work of the Women’s Lobby as well as six audiocassettes of Long Range Planning Meetings from 1984 and 1986 and a photograph album (1985–1988). Subseries 2, Subject Files, is an alphabetical arrangement by subject and includes legislative agendas, board meeting minutes, budget reports, fund raising reports, correspondence, directories, training manuals, articles, newsletters and photographs related to the activities of the Lobbyist Fund. Subseries 2, Subject Files, also includes three audiocassettes of Legislative Agendas (1986), one audiocassette of the Legislative Session from 1985 and four audiocassettes of the Montana Women’s Lobby on Legislative Hearings on Non-Gender Insurance (1985).
Series VII: Montana Women’s History Project, is divided into six subseries. Subseries 1, Correpsondence, is chronologically arranged. Subseries 2, Oral Histories of Montana Women, is arranged alphabetically and includes first hand accounts, interviews, transcripts, notes, newspaper clippings, and photographs of women from Montana and covers a range of topics including illegal abortion, work conditions, job training, and lesbian relationships. Subseries 3, Illegal Abortion in Montana Oral History Project, is arranged alphabetically by subject and contains materials about the experience of Montana women and abortion in Montana. Subseries 4, Subject Files, is arranged chronologically and contains research materials related to the creation and implementation of the Montana Women’s Oral History Project. Subseries 5, Publications, is chronologically arranged and contains newsletters, journal articles and newspaper clippings about the history of women in Montana as well as information about abortion, women’s studies, Native Americans, and economics. Subseries 6, Photographs, is arranged chronologically and includes photographs of women and families from a variety of archival repositories in Montana.
Series VIII: Newspaper Clippings (1970-1995) is a chronological sequence of articles related to the women’s liberation movement in Montana.
Series I: Women’s Resource Center, 1.2 linear feet, 1970-1992
Subseries 1: Administrative Records, 0.7 linear feet, 1972-1986
Subseries 2: Subject Files, 0.5 linear feet, 1970-1992
Series II: National Organization for Women, Missoula Chapter, 1.9 linear feet, 1979-1994
Subseries 1: Subject Files, 0.3 linear feet, 1979-1991
Subseries 2: Non-Gender Insurance, 1.6 linear feet, 1982-1994
Series III: Women’s Studies at the University of Montana, 0.8 linear feet, 1964-1999
Series IV: Montana Pro-Choice Coalition, 1.0 linear foot, 1971–1995
Subseries 1: Administrative Records, 0.6 linear feet, 1971-1989
Subseries 2: Abortion, 0.4 linear feet, 1973-1995
Series V: Women’s Liberation, 1.6 linear feet, 1954-1982
Series VI: Women’s Lobbyist Fund, 2.0 linear feet, 1978-1999
Subseries 1: Administrative Records, 0.9 linear feet, 1984-1991
Subseries 2: Subject Files, 1.1 linear feet, 1978-1999
Series VII: Montana Women’s Project, 1.9 linear feet, 1892-2000
Subseries 1: Correspondence, 0.3 linear feet, 1975-1987
Subseries 2: Oral Histories of Montana Women, 0.1 linear feet, 1900-1981
Subseries 3: Illegal Abortion in Montana Oral History Project, 0.3 linear feet, 1913-1996
Subseries 4: Subject Files, 0.7 linear feet, 1911-1948, 1970-1987
Subseries 5: Publications, 0.4 linear feet, 1951-2000
Subseries 6: Photographs, 0.1 linear feet, 1892-1914
Series VIII: Newspaper Clippings, 0.4 linear feet, 1970-1995
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
Personal collection of Diane Sands of women’s and feminist organizations in Montana as well as personal and academic research. Files were collected by Sands and resided in the Women’s Studies Department for several months before being delivered to the Archives in April of 2002.
Materials donated to the Archives between 2002 and 2005.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
University of Montana --Missoula--Alumni and alumnae; Illegal Abortion in Montana Oral History Project; Montana Pro-Choice Coalition; Montana Women's Oral History Project; Montana Women's Lobbyist Fund; National Organization for Women--Missoula Chapter; University of Montana --Missoula--Dept. of Women's Studies; University of Montana (Missoula, Mont.)--Women's Resource Center
Abortion--Montana--History; Feminism.--Montana; Oral history--Montana; Pro-choice movement--Montana; Women--Legal status, laws, etc. Montana; Women--Montana--History; Women--Montana--Social conditions; Women--Montana--Societies and clubs; Women--Montana--Interviews; Women's studies--Montana--Missoula
Interviews--Montana; Oral histories--Montana
Colleges and Universities; Student Life; Women; Missoula; Montana; Political Campaigns; Civic Activism; Oral Histories
Feminists--Montana
- Women's Resource Center, 1970-1992; Series I; 1.2 linear feet
  - Administrative Records, 1972-1986; Subseries 1; 0.7 linear feet
    - Financial Records, 1980-1984 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Meeting Notes and Agendas, 1976-1980 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Meeting Notes and Agendas, 1980-1982 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Meetings and Minutes, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1984 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Correspondence, Letters from Charlotte Bunch to Diane Sands, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Brown Bag Evaluations, 1982 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Brown Bag Evaluations, 1983 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Brown Bag Evaluations, undated (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Brown Bag Evaluations, undated (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Daily Log, Sept. - Dec. 1979 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Daily Log, Jan. - Feb. 1980 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Daily Log, Mar. - May 1980 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - Daily Log, June - July 1980 (Box-folder 1/14)
    - Daily Log, Aug. - Nov. 1980 (Box-folder 1/15)
    - Daily Log, Feb. - Nov. 1981 (Box-folder 1/16)
    - Daily Log, Apr. 1982 - Dec. 1982 (Box-folder 1/17)
    - Daily Log, Jan. - Aug. 1983 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Newsletters, Overview of Content of Newsletters, 1975-1986 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Subject Files, 1970-1992; Subseries 2; 0.5 linear feet
    - Abortion Rights, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Celebrations, Susan B. Anthony, Jeanette Rankin birthday celebrations 10th Anniversary of Women’s Center and Honoring Diane Sands, 1972-1992 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Clippings, Abortion Rights and Distribution of Birth Control Handbook, 1970, 1979, 1987, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Conferences, National Women’s Anthropology Newsletters, 1972-1982 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Conferences, Focus on Women, Women Aware Conference, 1975 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Conferences, Women and Power Conference, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Conferences, International Women’s Year Montana Meeting, 1977 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Conferences, Women and Technology Conference, 1979 (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Conferences, The New Right, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 3/11)
    - Conferences, Women and Technology Conference, 1980, 1982 (Box-folder 3/12)
    - Conferences, Conference for Women in Montana, 1980-1982 (Box-folder 3/13)
    - Conferences, Women in the Workforce Conference, Handbook, 1987 (Box-folder 3/14)
    - Conferences, Feminism in the 90s Conference, 1988 (Box-folder 3/15)
    - Human Rights Commission, Discrimination, undated (Box-folder 3/16)
    - Lectures, ‘Marxism and Feminism,’ a Lecture by Herbert Marcuse, 1974 (Box-folder 3/17)
    - Lobbying Materials, WRC Support Letters and SUB Board Allocations, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 3/18)
    - Lobbying Materials, 1978 (Box-folder 3/19)
    - Lobbying Materials, Battle for Office Space in the UC, 1980-1987 (Box-folder 3/20)
    - Lobbying Materials, Petitions Supporting the WRC, undated (Box-folder 3/21)
    - Northwest Women’s Studies Association, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 3/22)
    - Pregnancy Referral Services, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 3/23)
    - Pregnancy Referral Services, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 3/24)
    - Publications, Poems by Marge Piercy, 1964 (Box-folder 3/25)
    - Publications, Gilt Edge Magazine, 1975-1976, 1977 (Box-folder 4/1)
    - Strikes, Red Lion Striking Maids, 1977 (Box-folder 4/2)
    - Therapy/Counseling, undated (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Women’s Employment Network, Meeting Minutes, undated (Box-folder 4/4)
    - WORD Planning Meeting Agenda, 1987 (Box-folder 4/5)
- National Organization for Women, Missoula Chapter, 1979-1994; Series II; 1.6 linear feet
  - Subject Files, 1979-1991; Subseries 1; 0.3 linear feet
    - Publications, 1979, 1985 (Box-folder 4/6)
    - Lesbian Rights Resource Kit, 1982 (Box-folder 4/7)
    - Montana Chapter Founding Documents, Minutes and Newsletters, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 4/8)
    - NOW National Times, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 4/9)
    - NOW National Times, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 4/10)
    - Lesbian/Gay Rights, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 4/11)
    - Reports on Reagan Administration Impact on Women, 1984 (Box-folder 4/12)
    - Report on Comparable Wealth, 1985, 1991 (Box-folder 4/13)
    - Gender Gap Conference, 1988 (Box-folder 4/14)
    - It’s Her Business Handbook, 1988 (Box-folder 4/15)
    - ERA Posters, undated (Box-folder 4/16)
    - Plays, undated (Box-folder 4/17)
  - Non-Gender Insurance, 1982-1994; Subseries 2; 1.6 linear feet
    - Insurance, 1982-1985 (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Insurance, 1982-1985 (Box-folder 5/2)
    - Insurance, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Insurance, 1985 (Box-folder 5/4)
    - Insurance, 1985 (Box-folder 5/5)
    - Insurance, 1985-1994 (Box-folder 5/6)
    - Insurance, 1986 (Box-folder 5/7)
    - Insurance, 1986 (Box-folder 5/8)
    - Insurance, 1986 (Box-folder 5/9)
    - Insurance, 1986 (Box-folder 5/10)
    - Insurance, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 5/11)
    - Insurance, 1988 (Box-folder 5/12)
    - Constitutional Question, 1983 (Box-folder 6/1)
    - DC NOW Campaign, 1986 (Box-folder 6/2)
    - Hearing, Interim Legislative Committee #3, 1984 (Box-folder 6/3)
    - Implementation of Law, 1985 (Box-folder 6/4)
    - Implementation of Law, 1985 (Box-folder 6/5)
    - Implementation of Law, 1985 (Box-folder 6/6)
    - Legislative Session, 1983 (Box-folder 6/7)
    - Legislative Session, 1985 (Box-folder 6/8)
    - Legislative Session, 1985 (Box-folder 6/9)
    - Legislative Session, 1985 (Box-folder 6/10)
    - Legislative Session, 1985 (Box-folder 6/11)
    - Legislative Session, 1987 (Box-folder 6/12)
    - Legislative Session, 1987 (Box-folder 6/13)
    - Massachusetts NOW Campaign, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 7/1)
    - Maternity Coverage, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 7/2)
    - Minnesota Department of Commerce Report, 1984 (Box-folder 7/3)
    - Montana NOW Insurance Survey, 1985 (Box-folder 7/4)
    - Montana NOW Insurance Survey, 1985 (Box-folder 7/5)
    - Montana NOW Insurance Survey, 1985 (Box-folder 7/6)
    - Montana NOW Insurance Survey, 1985 (Box-folder 7/7)
    - Montana NOW Insurance Survey, 1985 (Box-folder 7/8)
    - Montana NOW Insurance Survey, 1985 (Box-folder 7/9)
    - Montana NOW Insurance Survey, 1985 (Box-folder 7/10)
    - Montana NOW Insurance Survey, 1985 (Box-folder 7/11)
    - Montana NOW Insurance Survey, 1985 (Box-folder 7/12)
    - Pennsylvania NOW Campaign, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 7/13)
    - Pennsylvania NOW Campaign, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 8/1)
    - Pennsylvania NOW Campaign, 1986 (Box-folder 8/2)
    - Pennsylvania NOW Campaign, 1989 (Box-folder 8/3)
    - Pennsylvania and Massachusetts NOW Campaigns, 1985 (Box-folder 8/4)
    - Publications, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 8/5)
    - Rules Hearing, September 1985 (Box-folder 8/6)
    - Rules Hearing, September 1985 (Box-folder 8/7)
    - Senate and House Committee, Testimony, 1985 (Box-folder 8/8)
    - Senate and House Committee, Testimony, 1985 (Box-folder 8/9)
    - Senate and House Committee, Testimony, 1985 (Box-folder 8/10)
    - Testimony, Non-Discrimination Insurance, Women’s Equity Action League, 1985 (Box-folder 8/11)
    - Western States Life Insurance Policies, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 8/12)
    - Women’s Lobbyist Fund, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 8/13)
    - Women’s Lobbyist Fund, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 8/14)
- Women’s Studies at the University of Montana, 1964-1999; Series III; 0.8 linear feet
  - Committees, Women in the Curriculum, Interdisciplinary Studies, 1973-1987 (Box-folder 9/1)
  - Courses, Materials from Feminist Theory, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 9/2)
  - Courses, Montana Assertiveness Collection, 1974 (Box-folder 9/3)
  - Courses, Chapter of Masters Thesis, Meredith Taylor, 1974 (Box-folder 9/4)
  - Courses, Diane Sands Coursework, 1974 (Box-folder 9/5)
  - Courses, Women’s Studies Course, 1974–1979 (Box-folder 9/6)
  - Courses, Human Sexuality and Social Work, Exams and Grades, 1975 (Box-folder 9/7)
  - Courses, Women’s History and Feminist Studies Materials, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 9/8)
  - Courses, Lesbian Feminism Theory Notes, 1979-1984 (Box-folder 9/9)
  - Courses, Women’s Studies Course Evaluations, 1980 (Box-folder 9/10)
  - Courses, Women’s Studies Registration Forms, 1981 (Box-folder 9/11)
  - Courses, Introduction to Women’s Studies Course Materials, 1981 (Box-folder 9/12)
  - Courses, Introduction to Women’s Studies Course Materials, 1981-1984 (Box-folder 9/13)